A Guide to the Wendy Bertrand Architectural Collection, 1954-2012
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Wendy Bertrand Architectural Collection, 1954-2012
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
Bertrand, Wendy
Ms2015-025
15 Cubic Feet 9 manuscript boxes, 1 small Hollinger box, 5 telescoping boxes, 2 flat boxes, 5 oversized folders
Wendy Bertrand is a registered architect, rug weaver, and author from Southern California. This collection documents her personal and professional activities between 1954-2012, including her architectural studies, travel, professional writing, textile projects, and career with the U.S. Navy and U.S. Forest Service.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The Wendy Bertrand Architectural Collection was donated to Special Collections in 2013.
Biographical Note
Wendy Bertrand is a registered architect, rug weaver, and author from Southern California. She studied at the École des Beau Arts in France from 1964–65 and graduated from the University of California, Berkeley (B.A. Architecture 1971, M.A. Architecture 1972). She has designed private residential structures and supervised large-scale engineering projects for the U.S. Navy (1973-1991) and U.S. Forest Service (1991-1994). Bertrand served in a variety of leadership roles throughout her career, including chair of the Quality of Worklife Committee for the U.S. Navy Public Works Center, Commissioner for her local Board of Architectural Examiners, and rating panelist for the City and County of San Francisco. She was an active participant in the Society of American Military Engineers and the Organization of Women Architects and Design Professionals. In 2008, Bertrand published Rug Retrospective: Nine Weaving Seasons 1999-2008 (updated in 2010), documenting her textile projects. In 2012, Bertrand published Enamored with place: as woman + as architect, a memoir of her experiences as a single mother working in a traditionally male profession. Her 2015 epilogue, If I Knew Then What I Know Now, reflects on the influences of gender in architectural practice and what the future might hold for women in architecture.
Scope and Content
This collection documents the professional and personal activities of Wendy Bertrand between 1954-2012. Comprised primarily of textual materials and architectural drawings with supporting photographs and ephemera, the collection documents Bertrand's study of art and architecture; her career as an architect, engineering advisor, and supervisor for the US Navy and US Forest service; her private practice and engagement in national organizations; her family life, personal networks, and community engagement; and her artistic endeavors in textiles, photography, and furniture design. Coverage includes correspondence, travel journals, education files, project records and business files, personal reflections on her career, manuscript drafts, research notes, photographs, exhibition boards, construction documents, architectural drawings, and ephemera.
External Sources:
http://wendybertrand.com/
Eyeonplace Press
Arrangement
Arrangement of these materials reflects the Standard Series for Architecture and Landscape Design Records (Shepherd and Lowell). The intellectual structure reflects the following series and subseries:
I. Personal Papers
A. Writings
B. Correspondence
C. School Work
D. Travel
E. Photographs
F. Activism
G. Hobbies and Family Records
II. Professional papers
A. Correspondence
B. Photographs
C. Writings
D. Reference Files
E. Presentations
F. Exhibits
G. Associations and Committee
H. Awards
I. Career Records
J. Continuing Education
III. Office Records
A. Naval Facilities Engineering Command, Western Division
B. Navy Public Works Center
C. U.S. Forest Service Pacific Southwest Region 5
IV. Project Records
A. Naval Facilities Engineering Command, Western Division
B. Navy Public Works Center
C. Independent Projects
Index Terms
Subjects:
International Archive of Women in Architecture (IAWA); Women architects -- California; Women -- History; History of Women in Architecture
Contents List
- Personal Papers
  - Writings
    - Journals/Writing Notebooks
      - 1981-1989 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - 1985-1989 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - 1990, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - 1996 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - 1996-1997 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - 1997 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - 1997-1998 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - 1998-1999 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - 1999-2000 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - 2000-2001 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - 2001 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - 2001-2002 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - 2002-2003 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - 2003 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - 2003-2004 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - 2004 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      - 2004-2009 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - 2006-2007 (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - 2007 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      - 2007 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      - 2009 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Enamored with place: as women + as architect
      - Correspondence w/ Ellen Perry Berkeley, 1973-2012 (Box 2, Folder 6)
      - Working W/ Writer Susan Bono, 2005-2006 (Box 2, Folder 7)
      - Various Editors 2007-2008 (Box 2, Folder 8)
      - Ellen Perry Berkeley Edits, Entire Manuscript, 2011 (Box 2, Folder 9-13)
    - Writing Workshop Publications, 2003-2004; 2011 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Remembrance of Friend, Jeannie Bancroft Urmston Branscomb (1942-2001), 2001 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Adieu Madame Moureau de Veaux, Souvenirs de Wendy Betrand,' June 2001 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Writing Samples (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Neighboring: Vignettes (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence
    - Correspondence - General, 1969-1999 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Correspondence w/ Ase Marstrander of Sweden, 1967-2000 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Correspondence w/ Curtis Holder, 1958-1960 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Memorabilia Relating to Curtis Holder, 1956 - Late 2000s (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Correspondence w/ Phyllis Eakin [Bertrand's Mother], 1979-2003 and undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence w/ Shey Shiung Sheu (Taiwan) + Huang Kising (Peking, China), 1975-1979 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - School Work
    - K-12
      - Elementary School (Box 3, Folder 3)
      - K-12 Report Cards (Box 3, Folder 4)
      - Photographs, High School, 1954-1959 (Box 3, Folder 5)
      - Diploma, High School, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 6)
      - Yearbook, High School, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 7)
      - High School Reunions, early 1960s, 1979, 2009 (Box 3, Folder 8)
      - Clippings and other memorabilia, high school, 1954-1959 (Box 3, Folder 9)
      - Writings, High School, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Higher Education
      - UC Santa Barbara
        - University of California [Berkeley and Santa Barbara] grade reports and transcripts (Box 3, Folder 11)
        - Economics - Geography, Spring 1962 (Box 3, Folder 12)
      - Alliance Francaise
        - Alliance Francaise records 1963-1964 (Box 3, Folder 13)
      - Ecole des Beaux-Arts, France
        - General, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 14)
        - Prep Book for Oral Examination in Architecture (French) (Box 3, Folder 15-16)
        - 18 drawings, Aix en Provence, Montpellier, France (1964-65) (Folder 1)
        - Solid geometry exercises, France, 1964-65 (Folder 1)
        - Unidentified school project, January 5, 1965 (Box 16)
          Scope and Contents
          Six sepia prints, including site plans, elevations, and details.
      - UC Berkeley
        - Arch 251 - 'Problems in Architecture,' Fall 1971 (Box 3, Folder 17)
        - Risk Maps --> Architecture (Box 3, Folder 18)
        - Arch. 121 - Field Diary, Summer 1968, Engineering Materials Laboratory, Arch S.O.M. (Box 3, Folder 19)
        - Environmental Design Four San Quentin Prison, Fall 1969 (Box 3, Folder 20)
        - 1962-1972, General (Box 3, Folder 21)
        - A Taste of the History of Architecture in18th Century France," September 1969 (Box 3, Folder 22)
        - M. Arch Comprehensive Examination, Topic: 'A User in Need: Women During Childbirth' (Box 3, Folder 23)
        - Untitled Project [Subject = Use of Street is Important to Residential Quality of Neighborhoods] (Box 3, Folder 24.25)
        - 102C - Design Project, Cornucopia Restaurant, Undated (Box 3, Folder 26)
        - Photographs - UC Berkeley museum Construction, Requriement for construction management Class, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 27)
        - ASA 125 ,1970; ARCH 269C, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 28)
        - Arch 202 "Educational Facilities" (Box 3, Folder 29)
        - UC Berkeley Diplomas, 1971 and 1972 (Box 3, Folder 30)
        - Photographic studies for course projects, 1967-72 (Box 3, Folder 31-32)
        - Photos of Richmond Coastline Study panels from her time at Richmond, CA planning dept (Box 3, Folder 33)
        - Photographic studies and print sheets, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 1)
        - Exhibit catalog, Prestini Sculptures, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 2)
        - Mounted photographs and exhibitions for course projects (Box 12)
        - Drawings, 1968 (Box 12)
        - Exhibit boards (15), 1968 (Folder 3)
  - Travel
    - Around the World Trip
      - Correspondence w/ Phyllis Eakin [Bertrand's Mother] Oct. 1959-April 1961 (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - Curt Holder Correspondence 2006 (Box 4, Folder 4)
      - Correspondence w/ Susan Eakin [Sister]1960-161 (Box 4, Folder 5)
      - Journals1960-1961 (Box 4, Folder 6)
      - Hostel & Vaccination Documents1960-1961 (Box 4, Folder 7)
      - Photographs 1960-1961 (Box 4, Folder 8)
      - Photographs & Negatives 1960-1961 (Box 4, Folder 9)
      - Slides (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - China, 1965-1967 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Australia, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Finland, 2001 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Photographs
    - Photographs (Personal) (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Negatives (Personal) (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Photographs (Family), 1940 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Photographs of other architects (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Textile Designs and Lamp Shades (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Activism
    - Gasquet, CA - Smith River Corridor, 1995-2007 (Box 4, Folder 19-24)
    - Letters to Editor, 1999-2010, + undated, re: local issues (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Hobbies and Family Records
    - Astrological Chart, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - "Bay to Breakers" Race Certificate, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - Bay Area Crochet and Knit Guild Brochures (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Woodworking, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - A. Rutherford Eakin [Bertrand's Father], 1981, 1996, & undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Phyllis Eakin, architecture course exam book, University of California San Diego, Dec 8, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Marriage to Alain Bertrand, 1964-2006 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Professional Papers
  - Professional correspondence, 1973-1995 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Photographs of Wendy and colleagues, 1970s-1980s (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Writings
    - "Quality Progress: Designing Quality into Work Life" (25:6, June 1992) (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - 1995 Strategic Planning Gasquet (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Letter to the editor about women in architecture (1972-1975) (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Organization of Women Architects Article, Feb-March 1996 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Reference Files
    - Subject File: Women in Architecture (1972-2009) (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Subject File: Women in Architecture (1973-1986) (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Subject File: Women in Architecture (1956-2010) (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Subject File: Women in Architecture (1974, 1990) (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Presentations
    - VHS: Interview with Wendy Betrand (sic) (20:00 dub) (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - VHS: Wendy Betrand, Follow-up People Speaking Training Sept. 91 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Design Forum '81: Women Up Front ("Interview the Government") (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Retirement Speech for Bill Bechtell, June 1, 1997 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Exhibits
    - Biographical Excerpt from "architects. Doing Other Things" (a. DOT) (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Associations and Committeees
    - Organization of Women Architects & Design Professionals, 1973-2003 (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - Architecture Organizations Dedicated to Women, 1975-2009 (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Society of American Military Engineers, 57th Annual National Meeting (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - Society of American Military Engineers, 57th Annual National Meeting, Photographs (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - Society of American Military Engineers, 57th Annual National Meeting, "Priorities Ahead" Manual and Notes (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - Society of American Military Engineers, 57th Annual National Meeting, "Priorities Ahead" Program, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Awards
    - Oakland YWCA Award, 6th Annual Salute to Women, 14 September 1989 (Box 5, Folder 25)
    - Oakland YWCA award plaque
    - Award: Federal Women's Program Committee (18 November 1976)
  - Career Records
    - Photo album, San Francisco Wine and Food Show (WSB International) (Box 5, Folder 26)
    - Architecture Licenses, 1989-2007 (Box 5, Folder 27)
    - BART-Traveler Behavior Studies, 1972-1973 (Box 5, Folder 28-29)
    - Job Search (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Resumes, 1978-1991 (Box 6, Folder 2-3)
    - Resumes, 1978, 1985-1991 (Box 6, Folder 4-6)
    - Wage History, 1983-1994 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - EEO Complaint (Box 6, Folder 8-10)
    - Salary Receipts and Paystubs (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Continuing Education
    - Transcripts and Certificates (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Management Courses (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - American Management Association Course - Management Skills for New Women Supervisors in the Public Sector (Box 6, Folder 14)
- Office Records
  - Western Division, Naval Facilities Engineering Command
    - Newsletters (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - WSB Business Card (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Correspondence and Clippings (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - Reports (Box 6, Folder 18-19)
    - Invitation to ribbon cutting ceremony for the Recruit In-Processing Building (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Navy Public Works Center, Oakland CA
    - Files, 1985-1991 (Box 7, Folder 1-2)
    - Files, 1989-1991 (Box 7, Folder 3-4)
    - Engineer-in-Charge (EIC) Guide, Training and Procedural Guidelines) (Box 7, Folder 5-7)
    - Photographs (Box 7, Folder 8-10)
    - Code 480, Engineering Record FY 1985-1988 (Box 7, Folder 11-12)
    - Code 480 Engineering Record, FY 1989-1990 (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Architectural Branch Annual Reports, 1987-1988 (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - Telephone chart/address book (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - Record book (job and personnel) (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - Annotated article "Managing Your Boss" (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - WSB Ratings and performance memos (Box 7, Folder 18-19)
    - Quality of Work Life - "Action - CCSS SIMA report" (Box 10, Folder 1-2)
    - Quality of Work Life Assessment accord (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Quality of Work Life Committee, 1988-1990 (Box 7, Folder 20-21)
    - Quality of Work Life Case Study for Quality Progress magazine, 1990 (Box 7, Folder 22)
    - Executive Management Development Program (Box 7, Folder 23)
    - Executive Management Development Program (Box 8, Folder 1-3)
    - Reorganization, 7-1989 to 10-1989 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Farewell Party (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Code 480 Memories 1 May 1991 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - U.S. Forest Service, Pacific Southwest Region 5
    - 1991 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - 1992 (Box 8, Folder 8-9)
    - 1993 (Box 8, Folder 10-11)
    - 1994 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Articles Re: Management, 1991-1993 (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Bertrand's Workplace Complaints, including a declaration for a class action complaint 1992-1996 (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - Bertrand Initiative: Forest Roads Program Funding Cards, 1992 (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - Bertrand Initiative: Professional Friends Brown Bag, 1991-1994 (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - Directories, 1990-1993 (Box 8, Folder 17)
    - Daily Diaries (Calendar), 1992-1993 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Plaque and Certificate, 1993-1994 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Memos and Reports re: Work place environment and sexual harassment, 1990-1992 (Box 9, Folder 3-5)
    - US Forest Service Application Packet (Box 9, Folder 6)
- Project Records
  - NAVFAC (WESTDIV)
    - Recruit In-Processing Facility, San Diego CA
      - Recruit In-Processing Facility, 1975 (Box 9, Folder 7)
      - Sepia prints of Recruit In-Processing Facility, 1975 (Box 14)
      - Construction drawings, Recruit In-Processing Facility, 1975 (Box 18)
    - Naval Air Station, Fallon NV
      - Family Housing, Naval Air Station (M-304), Fallon, NV, 1979 (Box 9, Folder 8)
      - Construction drawings, Family Housing, Naval Air Station (M-304), Fallon, NV, 1979 (Box 18)
    - Marine Corps Recruit Depot, San Diego CA
      - Photograph studies, Marine Core Recruit Depot, San Diego, CA (Box 11)
      - Drawings, Unaccompanied Enlisted Personnel Housing P 055, MCRD, San Diego, CA (Box 11)
      - Boarded presentation drawings, Unaccompanied Enlisted Personnel Housing P-210, MCRD, San Diego, CA (Box 11)
    - Marine Corps Air Station, Yuma AZ
      - Marine Corps Air Station Yuma, Earth Sunken Quad-Plex, 1982 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Navy Public Works Center
    - Dining Facility Renovation, 1989, Alamaeda CA (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - Marina Green, Naval Station Treasure Island, San Francisco, CA, late 1980s (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - Naval Supply Center, 1990s (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - Cafeteria Building 311, California (n.d.) (Box 9, Folder 14)
    - Unidentified project slides, 1986 (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Independent Projects
    - Central Shop and Warehouse District, 1983 Proposal (San Francisco Community College District and The City & County of San Francisco) (Box 9, Folder 16)
    - Hospelhorn/Bertrand Residence (695 Gasquet Flat Rd) (Box 9, Folder 17, Box 13)
    - Bertrand residence (478 27th street Block 6580 #23 R-2) (Box 9, Folder 18, Box 15)
    - Haritchabalet Residence, Kitchen Remodel, 2002-2003 (Box 9, Folder 19)
    - Zucker residence, 2138 North Navajo Lot 102, Flagstaff, AZ, 1998 (Box 17)
    - Hospelhorn residence, 411 27th Street, SF 94131 (Folder 4)
    - Lesiak residence (222 Granada Ave, El Granada, CA) (Box 9, Folder 20, Folder 5)